<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-04-02T16:08:54-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Perpetually Learning</title><subtitle>Brad Allen's personal blog. I love building things (and learning how to build new things). Preferably those that scale. Keywords: Product Management, Data Science, Data Engineering, Python, Stanford, Stanford GSB, Penn State, Pennsylvania, TFA, Teach For America, Bain, Embrace, Aclima, Peloton Technology, Mechatronics, C+
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Moving hosting from AWS to Github.</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/moving-to-github/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Moving hosting from AWS to Github." /><published>2020-02-14T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-02-14T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/moving-to-github</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/moving-to-github/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This article was written in 2017 during my time at SVDS. The article was first published on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.svds.com/customer-journey-set-success/&quot;&gt;SVDS Blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In the &lt;a href=&quot;https://bradaallen.github.io/customer-journey-success-part-1/&quot;&gt;introductory post&lt;/a&gt;, we walked through some examples of how SVDS has seen data capabilities determine the success of customer journey initiatives for our clients. In this post, we offer guidance on the data-related initiatives that you can start today to begin fostering closer ties with your customers—regardless of where you currently are in your specific state of development.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GH Pages:1. Use WSL, don’t mess with the devkits: https://kiazhi.github.io/blog/Working-with-Jekyll-and-Ruby-on-Windows-for-GitHub-Pages/#getting-started-with-jekyll-on-windows-10-using-windows-subsystem-for-linux&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use rbenv, don’t mess with bare installations: https://brainwipe.github.io/jekyll/hyde/ubuntu/2017/05/16/pulling-jekyll-teeth/&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make sure you are using the gh-pages dependencies for Ruby and Jekyll: https://pages.github.com/versions/* if you had other versions pre-installed, make sure you are loading from rbenv (eg, the shims in ruby and jekyll)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pick your theme; I like minimal mistakes: https://mmistakes.github.io/minimal-mistakes/docs/quick-start-guide/&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Follow this site for then creating your GH repo, testing locally, etc: https://help.github.com/en/github/working-with-github-pages/creating-a-github-pages-site-with-jekyll&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Set up a custom domain, if desired: https://help.github.com/en/github/working-with-github-pages/configuring-a-custom-domain-for-your-github-pages-site
Don’t forget the ~/.bashrc and . in jekyll new! rbenv init -, etc.
https://bryancshepherd.com/data-science/setting-bluehost-dns-github-jekyll-blog/  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;https://help.github.com/en/github/working-with-github-pages/configuring-a-custom-domain-for-your-github-pages-site 
https://help.github.com/en/github/working-with-github-pages/managing-a-custom-domain-for-your-github-pages-site
https://medium.com/@kimcodes/setting-up-a-web-page-with-github-pages-f77d45573ab2&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Quick notes on setting up a gh-pages blog using Windows 10.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Preparing Data Scientists to Develop in Agile.</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/developing-agile-data-scientists/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Preparing Data Scientists to Develop in Agile." /><published>2019-06-07T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-06-07T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/developing-agile-data-scientists</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/developing-agile-data-scientists/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This article was written in 2017 during my time at SVDS. The article was first published on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.svds.com/customer-journey-set-success/&quot;&gt;SVDS Blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In the &lt;a href=&quot;https://bradaallen.github.io/customer-journey-success-part-1/&quot;&gt;introductory post&lt;/a&gt;, we walked through some examples of how SVDS has seen data capabilities determine the success of customer journey initiatives for our clients. In this post, we offer guidance on the data-related initiatives that you can start today to begin fostering closer ties with your customers—regardless of where you currently are in your specific state of development.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lead in with Eric Colson blog: https://hbr.org/2019/03/why-data-science-teams-need-generalists-not-specialists&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;•	DS:
o	Programming &amp;amp; Architecture: 
	Ability to write tested, functional, modular code.
	Ability to work with git, in a gitflow environment.
	Can work in single- and distributed-machine environments with guidance.
o	ML:
	Understand the requirements of a full end-to-end ML solution (ie, target definition, ETL, KPI definition, training vs. scoring, model maintenance tooling)
	Has experience in 2 of 3: classification, regression, optimization. 
o	Consulting:
	Developing skills in workplanning, time management, written and verbal communication (pyramid principle – “tailoring the message”)
	Developing skills in knowing when to involve leadership to “unblock” vs. solving independently
•	SDS:
o	Programming &amp;amp; Architecture:
	Can perform code reviews.
	Can set up and manage the integrity of a codebase (refactor and redesign as needed, separate out cross-cutting functionality)
	Can identify the required solution architecture (infrastructure, programming languages req., storage patterns). – SDS2
o	ML:
	Can design a full E2E ML solution and offer alternatives based on resources, timeline, and client need.
o	Consulting:
	Focus is on module ownership – the ability to iterate a solution’s design to fit the client’s needs, plus the ability to design an E2E workplan for the module.
	Can begin to design consumable output (ie, feeding into campaign mgmt. system vs. Tableau vs. API vs. application)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;•	Overall (LDS+): Greater appreciation required for the benefits of clean code. Timelines and Gamma experience leads to “tactical programming” instead of “strategic programming.” We prioritize on quick output over the design of clean systems. This leads to bugs and complexity that make changes more difficult – this is where projects get burned.
•	Overall (LDS+): Better understanding up front of the technical tools required for a solution. Resources aren’t fungible and too much risk if the full team is implementing a new technology for the first time. 
•	Overall (LDS+): Agile Product Management. Designing full solutions early and adding functionality/complexity over time.
•	SDS: 
o	Wide variety in programming and engineering skillset. Many have gaps for what I would consider a high performing DS. Makes it difficult to work with them and focus on the logic of the problem.
o	Need greater “big picture focus” on how the solution will be owned and maintained by the client. In the solution design, lots of small complexity/optimizations that appear interesting over the course of a project, but end up running out of time, isn’t handed over well, or is not maintainable. Results orientation should be towards “what works 18mo after we leave.” 
	^^ translates into better workplanning, more curiosity around client dynamics (eg, req. process redesign, teaming, skills)
o	Need greater focus on the “so what” – being able to understand how we are creating value for the client and designing systems that prove the incremental gain
•	DS: 
o	Focus should be on gaining a mental map for what skills are required to be a successful DS. Can be myopic in going very deep in a few areas, with large gaps in other parts. This pattern (and rewarding it) may be a cause for the unevenness in the SDS cohort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;•	All Martin Fowler / XP programming books on writing clean code and continuous delivery (I can send a list).
o	Surviving Legacy Code: https://www.jbrains.ca/training/surviving-legacy-code/&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">How to iterate towards valuable, sustainable output.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">True Agile: Core to a DS Workflow.</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/data-science-and-agile/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="True Agile: Core to a DS Workflow." /><published>2019-04-18T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2019-04-18T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/data-science-and-agile</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/data-science-and-agile/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This article was written in 2017 during my time at SVDS. The article was first published on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.svds.com/customer-journey-set-success/&quot;&gt;SVDS Blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In the &lt;a href=&quot;https://bradaallen.github.io/customer-journey-success-part-1/&quot;&gt;introductory post&lt;/a&gt;, we walked through some examples of how SVDS has seen data capabilities determine the success of customer journey initiatives for our clients. In this post, we offer guidance on the data-related initiatives that you can start today to begin fostering closer ties with your customers—regardless of where you currently are in your specific state of development.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Include Tristan Handy stuff: https://blog.getdbt.com/4-questions-to-help-you-more-accurately-scope-analytics-engineering-projects/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Framing the approach: Data Science requires Agile &amp;amp; Product Management Skills&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Agile develops products faster by acknowledging the current uncertainty in the final solution. In my workplan, I am trading time for information that helps me manage this uncertainty. 
At the beginning of a model’s development, I don’t know:
The client’s preferred metrics for measurement
Business constraints that shape the necessary inputs/outputs
The right form factor that will ensure a tool is used
Any required changes to operational processes if a tool is not currently used (and associated resistance to change)
The greatest uncertainty should be “pulled forward” the farthest. Things that have material risk on the outcome should be (1) broken down into tests that (2) generate information that (3) allow for decision-making under greater certainty.
Acknowledging uncertainty is the key differentiator from an Agile and a waterfall process. The fact that my original plan could be wrong is the only reason iterations or adjustments are necessary. J
Erroneous assumptions can be very dangerous. If I assume a fact without designing a test, I am propagating the risk that I could be wrong “throughout” the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;By having a solution-mindset, and by trying to define clear product and technical requirements - I can then build slices of functionality that allow me to iterate towards a final solution.
Establish an MVP and build complexity over time. Google’s Rules of ML suggest starting after heuristics become too complex.
UI/UX and “core” (technical) functionality can be developed separately and in parallel. Each informs the other and is driven by usability. Looks like vs. Works like.
For UI/UX and systems design, design thinking is powerful. Particularly: 
Prioritizing visual tools (eg, wireframes, excel mockups) for feedback
Using user feedback to argue for change (BCG tool recommendations are made “on behalf of the user”)
Effective use of divergent + convergent thinking modes when brainstorming (called out to me by BCG Classics as a particularly powerful method)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Internal priority #1: Technical debt is a killer - need to trust the process.
Clean code really pays off - it reduces team velocity and makes it hard to create options
Code Spikes
Good PR process - complexity is added in small chunks. 
Sprint Goals need to be output driven. DS and SDS can have a tendency to be task oriented; it makes acceptance criteria less valuable and can lead to reduced productivity.
User Stories shouldn’t be more than 1-2 story points. Story Points are used to size work during sprints. They aren’t a tool to measure a developer’s productivity. User Stories shouldn’t bleed between sprints.
Have a Plan B that is viable. Creating options is what makes Agile work work well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;External priority #1: Communication in cross-functional teams is paramount&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Keep high transparency with the business. Onboard them into the “back-office” work of model building and management.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;They should know they are on a learning journey, and what we are finding together.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Always be clear - to everyone - on the definition of “done.”
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;And what level of “done” is appropriate for the problem at hand.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;A key client understanding is on the tradeoffs between flexibility and automation.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nobody should believe the model is a “black box.”
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Code is logic. If it can’t be explained clearly, it’s poor logic.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;We have a lot of smart people - when we do this, we deny ourselves the opportunity for good feedback.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What makes this particularly challenging is how orthogonal DS is - and its heavy reliance on apprenticeship – both sides are gaining experience and may not have the language yet to communicate effectively.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Defining done” is a common source of frustration between Classics and Gamma. 
Eg, the difference between the same output but where the code is (1) a rough script, vs (2) functional/modular/parametric, vs. (3) tested, vs. (4) automated
https://www.oreilly.com/radar/lessons-learned-turning-machine-learning-models-into-real-products-and-services/&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Or, 'how I got good at managing expectations under uncertainty.'</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Is Your Customer Journey Set Up for Success? Part II.</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/customer-journey-success-part-2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is Your Customer Journey Set Up for Success? Part II." /><published>2018-07-10T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-07-10T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/customer-journey-success-part-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/customer-journey-success-part-2/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This article was written in 2017 during my time at SVDS. The article was first published on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.svds.com/customer-journey-set-success/&quot;&gt;SVDS Blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In the &lt;a href=&quot;https://bradaallen.github.io/customer-journey-success-part-1/&quot;&gt;introductory post&lt;/a&gt;, we walked through some examples of how SVDS has seen data capabilities determine the success of customer journey initiatives for our clients. In this post, we offer guidance on the data-related initiatives that you can start today to begin fostering closer ties with your customers—regardless of where you currently are in your specific state of development.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;customer-journeys-allow-for-a-holistic-experience&quot;&gt;Customer journeys allow for a holistic experience&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A senior marketer’s ability to find and create valuable experiences for customers has grown dramatically in recent years. Beyond the traditional responsibilities of brand and creative management, senior marketers (such as CMOs, Brand Managers, and Product Marketing Managers) now use analytics to track customer interactions, measure the quality of engagement, and determine the effectiveness of an enormous range of different marketing tactics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marketers often map out a &lt;a href=&quot;https://hbr.org/2015/11/competing-on-customer-journeys&quot;&gt;“customer journey”&lt;/a&gt; in order to manage successful engagements. The customer journey is the complete sum of experiences that your customers go through when interacting with your company and brand—mapping out these interactions gives you a holistic view of how customers engage with your company. While many marketers focus on developing positive interactions, a customer journey is a plan that focuses on how a series of engagements can generate momentum from awareness, to sale, to ongoing loyalty and advocacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;creating-customer-journey-opportunities-with-data&quot;&gt;Creating customer journey opportunities with data&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At SVDS, we have seen leaders use data to drive more useful customer engagements—first and foremost by recognizing their need to embrace change. There is a big shift taking place, and that shift will become the new normal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should be trying to learn quickly, and fail fast. Companies that are able make the best use of their data and infrastructure earlier than their competition are at an advantage—both with regard to increased customer loyalty and improvements in new product development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a &lt;a href=&quot;https://bradaallen.github.io/customer-journey-success-part-1/&quot;&gt;November 2015 Harvard Business Review article&lt;/a&gt; on the customer journey, the authors stated that, “Best practitioners aim not just to improve the existing journey but to expand it, adding useful steps or features.” As mentioned in the examples earlier in this post, we have seen the same trend: clients who can harness their data to create effective customer experiences often make further investments toward developing their capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are data-related initiatives that you can begin pursuing today to develop stronger relationships with your customers. Make an honest assessment of where you stand now, and find yourself in the sections below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;if-you-are-starting-from-scratch&quot;&gt;If you are starting from scratch:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Common Challenges&lt;/em&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Redefining decision-making based on insights&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Identifying single points of ownership&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Common Solutions&lt;/em&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Focus on top-down buy-in. Without recognition from leadership, data initiatives will struggle to get relevance with business users and may be piecemeal efforts, diminishing the value of investment.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;if-you-are-performing-early-project-identification&quot;&gt;If you are performing early project identification:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Common Challenges&lt;/em&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Mapping out customer journey initiatives&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Identifying single points of ownership&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Common Solutions&lt;/em&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Get alignment on the full picture. It is important to be able to articulate the “full view” of the customer experience as it has a large effect on decision making. For example, only tracking successful interactions would lead to very different conclusions than understanding users that “turn away.”&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Plan for iteration. It often takes time to understand where your map does and does not match your customers’ realities.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Start small. Change can be incremental—look for low-hanging fruit.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;if-you-are-establishing-customer-visibility&quot;&gt;If you are establishing customer visibility:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Common Challenges&lt;/em&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Data integration&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Common Solutions&lt;/em&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Prioritize data collection in tandem with journey mapping. In instrumentation, it is important to know what behaviors you can collect directly from customers and what behaviors you have to infer based on their actions. This influences what additional data sources you include to support decisions you make for the business.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Seek to reuse and extend data services. Developing known, validated, and consistent data assets for your business increases their utility and dramatically improves trust in the developed insights across the organization.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;if-you-are-optimizing-for-growth&quot;&gt;If you are optimizing for growth:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Common Challenges&lt;/em&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Personalization and automation&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Common Solutions&lt;/em&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Enable advanced analytics. Optimize for automation to create feedback loops and self-learning capabilities that make it easy to identify and capitalize on growth opportunities.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What steps are you taking to strengthen your customer engagement strategies through better use of data?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Practical recommendations for any level of sophistication.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Is Your Customer Journey Set Up for Success? Part I.</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/customer-journey-success-part-1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is Your Customer Journey Set Up for Success? Part I." /><published>2018-07-03T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-07-03T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/customer-journey-success-part-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/customer-journey-success-part-1/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This article was written in 2017 during my time at SVDS. The article was first published on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.svds.com/customer-journey-set-success/&quot;&gt;SVDS Blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;customer-journeys-allow-for-a-holistic-experience&quot;&gt;Customer journeys allow for a holistic experience&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A senior marketer’s ability to find and create valuable experiences for customers has grown dramatically in recent years. Beyond the traditional responsibilities of brand and creative management, senior marketers (such as CMOs, Brand Managers, and Product Marketing Managers) now use analytics to track customer interactions, measure the quality of engagement, and determine the effectiveness of an enormous range of different marketing tactics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marketers often map out a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forrester.com/Customer-Journey&quot;&gt;“customer journey”&lt;/a&gt; in order to manage successful engagements. The customer journey is the complete sum of experiences that your customers go through when interacting with your company and brand—mapping out these interactions gives you a holistic view of how customers engage with your company. While many marketers focus on developing positive interactions, a customer journey is a plan that focuses on how a series of engagements can generate momentum from awareness, to sale, to ongoing loyalty and advocacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.salesforce.com/blog/2014/11/new-report-salesforce-marketing-cloud-linkedin-state-marketing-leadership.html&quot;&gt;Salesforce report&lt;/a&gt;, nearly all senior level marketers agree that a comprehensive journey map is absolutely critical or very important to their business. At the same time, the report mentions that this map has largely been an aspiration for marketers—in part due to siloed business teams and a disjointed view of customer data, only 29% of enterprise companies would rate themselves as very effective or effective at creating a cohesive journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Senior marketers should take the responsibility for this challenge head on; to be successful in creating a useful map, you will also need to be the leader of the technical and analytical development of their teams. You should have an intuition for how data can enhance, track, and articulate the customer experience—as this intuition creates new possibilities for the type of relationships companies can have with their customers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this first post, we’ll walk through some examples of how we have seen data capabilities determine the success of customer journey initiatives for our clients. In &lt;a href=&quot;https://bradaallen.github.io/customer-journey-success-part-2/&quot;&gt;subsequent posts&lt;/a&gt;, we’ll also offer guidance on the data-related initiatives that you can start today to begin fostering closer ties with your customers—regardless of where you currently are in your specific state of development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-can-your-data-do-for-you&quot;&gt;What can your data do for you?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve seen data play various roles in creating strong customer engagements. Here’s a look at just a few.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;optimize-against-competing-outcomes-using-effectively-stitched-data-social-gaming&quot;&gt;Optimize against competing outcomes using effectively stitched data (Social Gaming)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many businesses, legacy and heterogeneous systems are a challenge for creating an integrated customer experience—the data is often structured with a narrow lens on a specific product or domain. We worked with a social gaming company facing this challenge: they wanted to create a cohesive customer experience across all their games by extending the preferential treatment that loyal customers receive for their favorite games to new games on the platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a per-game basis, our client was technically sophisticated—they could build out events, correlate performance with targeted marketing strategies, and articulate the effectiveness of different campaigns. However, this sophistication fell apart at the organization-wide level. After several acquisitions and the use of third party licensing for games, the company found itself with a broken analytical architecture—each game optimized for itself, but there was a lot of opportunity in optimizing across the business. By supporting the integration of different data from different silos, the new architecture enabled the company to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Increase customer satisfaction by rewarding loyalty.&lt;/em&gt; By not being able to establish a single view of their customers, our client was continually losing opportunities to tailor experiences for their customers. For example, high-paying customers that had “preferred” status for certain games would return to being “unknown” when they started playing new games. By helping the client carry customer status across games, players will have greater satisfaction and loyalty.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Improve game development by understanding interaction patterns.&lt;/em&gt; Some of the most important metrics in gaming—e.g., alliances and teaming—are challenging to measure. Breaking down silos allowed the client to utilize novel sources of data, like gaming chats, to articulate a “web of influence” and its role in engagement and profitability.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By reframing the customer journey as an experience that transcends individual games—and developing a supporting data architecture—our client was able to both develop an engine for growth and improve profitability on an individual basis, by both reducing the acquisition cost (UAC) of customers and increasing their lifetime value (LTV).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;redefine-your-brand-and-product-suite-with-a-more-modern-architecture-digital-entertainment&quot;&gt;Redefine your brand and product suite with a more modern architecture (Digital Entertainment)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take a look at the data sources you’re using in your marketing efforts and you may find some unexpected insights. For example, is there untapped value in your existing customer relationships? A digital entertainment company wanted to develop a modern database architecture that would allow them to understand user consumption at both a customer and population-level—at a microsecond granularity.
Redesigning the client’s architecture to identify and articulate the customer’s consumption patterns ultimately gave the client vastly more usable data about their customers, which led to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;New customer offerings.&lt;/em&gt; Our client used these new capabilities to develop more effective cross-selling opportunities and to develop products that provide guidance to content providers.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Improved strategic decision making.&lt;/em&gt; This view of consumption informed large strategic bets for the organization—for example, the decision to give away existing products for free in return for increased engagement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The client had always had tremendous potential to understand customer engagement and consumption patterns—they were a portal for millions of users. However, their existing platform was limited by its underlying technology and a myopic view of the role of data. In their original product offering, the collected data was not necessarily perceived to have inherent value. We find this type of oversight to be common for marketers beginning to build analytics within their teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: This concept of “instrumentation”—the process of logging and tracking customer interactions—is important when creating an engagement plan. Instrumentation creates a more nuanced understanding of what customers find valuable about your products and services. For our client, this instrumentation influenced their entire business: from feature development, to sales, to pricing, and even to marketing copy about the efficacy of their existing product suite. Instrumentation is so important, in fact, that it is something we at SVDS specifically assess when considering the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.svds.com/understanding-your-data-maturity/&quot;&gt;data maturity of a business&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;update-back-office-processes-to-redefine-customer-expectations-national-retailer&quot;&gt;Update back-office processes to redefine customer expectations (National Retailer)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work that begins in the marketing department often extends to influence other parts of a business. In one example, we worked with a traditional brick and mortar retail client that was in the process of developing their digital presence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As their customers began to spend more time purchasing items online, our client realized that they would need new capabilities to support new types of interactions—for example, granularity in tracking inventory. When creating its online presence, our client found itself frequently selling under-stocked items from the website, and then had to follow them up with costly gift card apologies to disappointed customers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We helped the client gain an understanding of their inventory baseline and establish a real-time view of changes in supply and demand. This allowed the business as a whole to establish new customer relationships and a leaner efficiency:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Customer interaction with the brand.&lt;/em&gt; E-commerce has developed some great features to incent purchasing behavior—we have all experienced messages like, “There are only 3 items left in stock!” or “Order by 11:59pm Tuesday to get by Christmas.” Our client’s new modern inventory infrastructure allowed them to create similar features, increasing trust and confidence in the brand.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Reduced working capital.&lt;/em&gt; In the past, a granular level of detail—across stores, channels, and partners (e.g., third party sellers)—was not required from legacy operations. In developing a new system, our client was able to serve items that were stocked-out in their web distribution centers from stores in close proximity to the buyers. This allowed our client to reduce their buffer stock and protect against obsolescence.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For our retail client, marketing’s strategic influence and digital leadership forced growth in other parts of the business that benefited customers and improved the company’s competitive position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;next-steps&quot;&gt;Next Steps&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How is your company taking steps to strengthen their customer engagement strategies through better use of data?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Case studies from high performing transformations.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Data Maturity: Technology is Not Enough</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/technology-isnt-everything/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Data Maturity: Technology is Not Enough" /><published>2018-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-05-15T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/technology-isnt-everything</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/technology-isnt-everything/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This article was co-authored along with Scott Kurth in 2017, based on our experience at SVDS. The article was first published on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.svds.com/value-centered-data-maturity/&quot;&gt;SVDS Blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;success-with-data-involves-managing-strengths-and-weaknesses&quot;&gt;Success with data involves managing strengths and weaknesses&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The great data rush is well and truly under way. Across virtually every industry, companies large and small are committing serious money to standing up their data infrastructure, beefing up capabilities, and hunting for the value hidden in their data—but often without a clear plan. No wonder that many of the business leaders we speak with suspect their initiatives are underperforming. The complaint we hear most frequently, regardless of industry, is that technology investments aren’t generating the expected returns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.svds.com/first-steps-strategy/&quot;&gt;previous post on data maturity&lt;/a&gt;, we discussed a company that was just embarking on a transformation: launching a new services business and building data capabilities to support that business. But what if you’re not starting from the beginning? What if you’ve already been embracing new technology, conducting pilots, and launching new analytical platforms? Recently, we were working with a Fortune 500 industrial company in the midst of developing software services to improve product R&amp;amp;D and enrich the customer experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their goal was to &lt;a href=&quot;https://svds.com/building-a-data-driven-culture/&quot;&gt;use data to empower decision makers&lt;/a&gt; across every part of the organization to make robust, data-driven choices. The company had great talent, technical vision, and infrastructure. &lt;strong&gt;Still, they weren’t generating the progress they would have liked at a rate they would have expected. What was wrong?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sometimes-the-business-can-hold-good-technology-behind&quot;&gt;Sometimes, the business can hold good technology behind&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working with our client to articulate their overall data maturity shined a light on areas requiring attention to get the most of their technology investments:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Missing links between projects and metrics:&lt;/em&gt; The initiative’s overall success was being measured by a single metric that they could only begin tracking in 2020—at the completion of the transformation. This led to significant uncertainty within project teams building new capabilities and platforms. Many teams were unsure where their analytical work fit in the big into the larger efforts and, more importantly, whether they were contributing to the overall success of the transformation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lack of cross-functional teams:&lt;/em&gt; The analytical infrastructure built by the engineering team was impressive, but was sorely underutilized. The data scientists had not been trained to use it and did not know how to access it. We heard from an analytics manager: “Seventy percent of my team’s time is spent on writing UDFs and Pig scripts to access data!” Creating teams that facilitated collaboration between engineers and data scientists was an opportunity for quick productivity gains with expensive talent.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Siloed business functions:&lt;/em&gt; Teams felt a lack of clear objectives that stemmed from communication and information sharing issues with other teams. For example, one team integral to product development described their view of the future as “a dusty window.” Business units on the consumption side of application development experienced very uneven usage of analytical tools. Strengthening these partnerships was crucial as the overarching project’s success relied specifically on strong analytical capabilities throughout the entire organization.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In working together, we helped the industrial company link their data and analytical capabilities with their ultimate business objectives, allowing them to create the right metrics to truly understand their progress. We helped them improve their devops capabilities and better integrate their engineering and data science teams. Collectively, this helped them break down technical and organizational siloes that were hampering progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understanding the uneven maturity of their capabilities across people, process, and systems gave them the answers they needed to the question on everyone’s minds: How can we see real results faster? A view of the current state of maturity along with a clear roadmap for success creates a baseline and a way to measure progress.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Knowing what to do with it is what matters most.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Understanding Your Data Maturity</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/understanding-data-maturity/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Understanding Your Data Maturity" /><published>2018-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-05-01T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/understanding-data-maturity</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/understanding-data-maturity/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This article was co-authored along with Scott Kurth in 2017, based on our experience at SVDS. The article was first published on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.svds.com/understanding-your-data-maturity/&quot;&gt;SVDS Blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-effective-are-you-with-your-capabilities&quot;&gt;How &lt;em&gt;effective&lt;/em&gt; are you with your capabilities?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Businesses today are experiencing rapid change, inside and outside of Silicon Valley. Even coffee isn’t immune—just last year, Starbucks crossed the threshold of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2016-03-30/starbucks-takes-its-pioneering-mobile-phone-app-to-grande-level&quot;&gt;more than 20% of transactions being done in their mobile application&lt;/a&gt;. Data is the currency of &lt;a href=&quot;https://svds.com/optimizing-your-digital-strategy/&quot;&gt;digital transformation&lt;/a&gt;, and data capabilities are the battlefield influencing market share and profitability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No two situations are the same, but at SVDS we have found one truism: making a data transformation successful requires much more than simply getting the technology right. Across a variety of industries and operations, we consistently find the influence of systems and people to be deciding factors. This is one of the reasons why we developed our &lt;a href=&quot;https://svds.com/what-are-you-doing-with-your-data/&quot;&gt;Data Maturity Model&lt;/a&gt; — a tool for understanding how well your data capabilities create value for your business, across people, process, and systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;data-maturity-in-practice&quot;&gt;Data maturity in practice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data maturity is a useful tool for measuring the progress being made against your transformation. Recently, we were working with a multi-billion dollar industrial device company that was just beginning their Internet of Things (IoT) transformation: integrating software services with their physical devices. The vision was set and small experiments were being run throughout the organization—but the real work of building had not yet begun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The company’s overarching strategy made a lot of sense—building a higher-margin services business from the key position their devices play in their customers’ workflows. We were asked to help them develop a data strategy and accompanying architecture to make that possible. Fundamentally, they needed a plan to use analytics and device data to create new services their clients would value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this company certainly had major technology investments in its future, some of the most urgent things necessary for this transformation to be successful had little to do with technology:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;New incentives to change required:&lt;/em&gt; Like many established product companies, the organization was structured around distinct, mature product lines. With very different P&amp;amp;Ls and incentives, we were told: “Careers are made within the business units, not the company.” There was an inherent skepticism for investing in unproven growth, especially if the effort was performed by a centralized function.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lack of experience with data rights:&lt;/em&gt; At this time, a very small percentage of overall revenue was produced through software. To sidestep questions of license management, the default behavior was to “make stuff free so that we do not have to create licenses.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;New customer relationships (and approach to product development):&lt;/em&gt; Getting the most value from device data meant integrating it with some of the customers’ own data sources to provide greater context to end users. This meant expanding or revisiting customer relationships to embrace data sharing, requiring updates to processes in sales management (i.e., around channel or partnership agreements) and overarching application strategies (e.g., creating standards and cultivating ISV ecosystems).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In working together, we helped the industrial product company identify solutions for incentivizing technical investment. We identified policies required around data ownership, custody, and consent as a precursor to becoming an integrator and reseller in the supply chain of data services. We helped them update their architecture to support these services. It is not uncommon for an SVDS maturity assessment to reveal a broad set of opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, our client was equipped with a broader perspective on what they needed to launch their software business and a roadmap to build all aspects of their data capabilities, ensuring that their transformation would be more successful. A clear roadmap helped them fill in the gaps between here and there, illuminating the concrete steps they needed to achieve their vision. Although transformation does not have a fixed end point, milestones are important—change should be incremental enough that the organization can see progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although it won’t give you a full picture of your organization, these exercises are a good starting point to help you gain a better sense of your company’s data maturity and spark productive exchanges with your colleagues. Is your organization using data just for generating reports or focusing on use cases in mission-critical areas? Or is it putting data first in every business activity? Knowing where you stand will increase your understanding of your organization’s potential, provide a baseline for measuring progress, and give you a framework for thinking about your data operations and how they might compare with the competition’s and your industry’s as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">First steps in a data strategy.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Digital Economy Part III: Technology requires deeper integration into our work lives.</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/digital-economy-part-3/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Digital Economy Part III: Technology requires deeper integration into our work lives. " /><published>2017-06-23T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-06-23T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/digital-economy-part-3</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/digital-economy-part-3/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;These articles are part of exploration that started in late 2015 and early 2016. It was a confusing time: autonomous vehicles and Boston Dynamics were frequently in the news and OpenAI was just formed to make sure that the “march towards AGI was safe.” UBI was actively being discussed by Sam Altman and Ray Kurzweil was promoting 10x / exponential thinking. At the same time, economists like Robert Gordon were arguing that we were actually living in a time of low progress.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I tried to develop my own perspective on what was happening, with key conclusions presented &lt;a href=&quot;https://bradaallen.github.io/digital-economy-intro/&quot;&gt;at this link&lt;/a&gt;. Greater detail supporting other conclusions can be found in &lt;a href=&quot;https://bradaallen.github.io/digital-economy-part-1/&quot;&gt;Part I&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://bradaallen.github.io/digital-economy-part-2/&quot;&gt;Part II&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;labor-challenge-todays-digital-technologies-have-only-had-a-marginal-effect-on-worker-productivity&quot;&gt;Labor Challenge: Today’s digital technologies have only had a marginal effect on worker productivity.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of the consumer benefits from smartphones, Google searches, and Facebook do not lead to direct commercial growth in the economy: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.brookings.edu/bpea-articles/does-the-united-states-have-a-productivity-slowdown-or-a-measurement-problem/&quot;&gt;consumers are now more productive in how they use their personal time&lt;/a&gt;. Likewise, many of the current advancements being made in CS today (e.g., natural language processing, computer vision) support discovery and search—that is, they primarily strengthen existing ICT value propositions for technology businesses. IT has not been as meaningful for what people do with their time at work as we might have hope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The things at which Google and its peers excel, from Internet search to mobile software, are changing how we work, play and communicate, yet have had little discernible macroeconomic impact.…Transformative innovation really is happening on the Internet. It’s just not happening elsewhere.” 
– &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/beyond-the-internet-innovation-struggles-1439401576&quot;&gt;Greg Ip, Wall Street Journal, August 12, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a macroeconomic perspective, McKinsey researchers recently examined 22 industries to measure “digital potential”— including both investment and the use of technology to change how work is done. Some industries, like technology, media and financial services, were well along, while others, like healthcare and hospitality, trailed. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/2016/06/06/business/why-the-economic-payoff-from-technology-is-so-elusive.html?mwrsm=Email&amp;amp;_r=0&quot;&gt;Only 18 percent of the American economy is living up to its “potential,”&lt;/a&gt; the report concluded. “…And if lagging industries do not catch up, we will not see much of a change in national economic statistics,” said James Manyika, a director of the McKinsey Global Institute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This concept of “digital potential” implies that the use of technology will provide new services and features that consumers value, and that corporations can provide at a profit over today’s operating models. Often, neither of these assumptions prove true:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;New technology isn’t implicitly better.&lt;/em&gt; Most new digitization efforts need to fit into the pre-existing user workflow to have a chance at adoption. Technology changes generally stick best when they have a &lt;a href=&quot;http://miter.mit.edu/articleentrepreneurship-technology-push-vs-market-pull/&quot;&gt;“pull mechanism”&lt;/a&gt;; as an example of this, interactive whiteboards (in 45% of schools in 2013) &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.edsurge.com/news/2013-10-22-lessons-from-the-downfall-of-interactive-whiteboards&quot;&gt;largely failed to be adopted by teachers&lt;/a&gt; even with significant investment from school administrators.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Half-efforts may fail and be worse than having done nothing at all.&lt;/em&gt; Many legacy businesses are required to completely rethink their operations to take advantage of digital opportunities — &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.vox.com/a/new-economy-future/technology-productivity&quot;&gt;companies need to be designed to solve these problems&lt;/a&gt;. This level of systems thinking is difficult to do: there are personnel problems, workflow problems, organizational problems, regulatory problems, amongst others. Taking advantage of IT in a company is really, really hard.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-does-it-all-mean&quot;&gt;What does it all mean&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, none of this is to say that digital transformation isn’t possible. Industries throughout the supply chain from factory to retailing have already been substantially reorganized to reduce inventory, waste, and headcount; and IT-supported efficiencies in middle management and administrative support have been exploited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Needle-moving” changes require deep shifts in how businesses operate - for example, enabling experimentation, building internal software teams focused on removing “toil”, and Agile planning methodologies. These efforts often require a leap of faith from decision makers who have historically been successful without requiring any of those tools. It is a huge challenge to find the leadership, political will, and talent that can guide an organization through the pain of transformation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additional research, perspective, and detail can be found in the following supporting articles:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bradaallen.github.io/digital-economy-intro/&quot;&gt;Intro: Creating a general framework for current opportunities and challenges.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bradaallen.github.io/digital-economy-part-1/&quot;&gt;Part I: We are in a time of slow productivity and strong incumbents.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bradaallen.github.io/digital-economy-part-2/&quot;&gt;Part II: Aging &amp;amp; unproven learning models are headwinds to growth.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My goal in putting this together was to clarify my own thinking - and to present it in a way that can be challenged and deepened by others. I would be grateful to learn what may resonate (or differ) from your personal perspectives and work.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">What's changed in our personal lives also needs to change in our 9-5s.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Digital Economy Part II: Aging &amp;amp; Unproven Learning Models are Headwinds to Growth.</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/digital-economy-part-2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Digital Economy Part II: Aging &amp; Unproven Learning Models are Headwinds to Growth." /><published>2017-06-06T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-06-06T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/digital-economy-part-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/digital-economy-part-2/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;These articles are part of exploration that started in late 2015 and early 2016. It was a confusing time: autonomous vehicles and Boston Dynamics were frequently in the news and OpenAI was just formed to make sure that the “march towards AGI was safe.” UBI was actively being discussed by Sam Altman and Ray Kurzweil was promoting 10x / exponential thinking. At the same time, economists like Robert Gordon were arguing that we were actually living in a time of low progress.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I tried to develop my own perspective on what was happening, with key conclusions presented &lt;a href=&quot;https://bradaallen.github.io/digital-economy-intro/&quot;&gt;at this link&lt;/a&gt;. Greater detail supporting other conclusions can be found in &lt;a href=&quot;https://bradaallen.github.io/digital-economy-part-1/&quot;&gt;Part I&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://bradaallen.github.io/digital-economy-part-3/&quot;&gt;Part III&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;aging-populations-are-an-increasing-share-of-the-overall-population-creating-challenges&quot;&gt;Aging populations are an increasing share of the overall population, creating challenges.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Noted in Part I, weak general innovation is one driver of low economic growth. Changes affecting the makeup of our labor force will provide &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wsj.com/articles/for-economy-aging-population-poses-double-whammy-1470249965&quot;&gt;further drags on productivity&lt;/a&gt; Two factors are an aging labor force and a “skills challenge” for remaining labor attempting keeping up with dynamic changes in technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aging labor forces have a tremendous effect on productivity. On average, every 10% increase in the share of a state’s population over the age of 60 reduced per capita growth in gross domestic product by 5.5%. This is explained by two factors. First (and most intuitively), as more workers retire, the labor force grows more slowly. This explains one-third of the 5.5% growth hit. But the (surprising) bigger effect is through reduced productivity—that is, output per hour—of the remaining workers. Mentorship matters! Experienced employees make their less-experienced reports more productive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This effect of aging on productivity will be even more pronounced as McKinsey estimates that we are entering an era of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mckinsey.com/global-themes/employment-and-growth/the-world-at-work&quot;&gt;slow-growing or even shrinking labor forces (see image below)&lt;/a&gt;. To maintain historical rates of GDP growth, it’s estimated that the “aging advanced” economies would need to increase productivity growth by about 60 percent of historical levels, to about 1.9 percent annually. This is a rate that hasn’t been reached since the 1960s. As an extreme example, the Southern Europe cluster will face an even steeper challenge: these economies would need to double their 0.7 percent rate of productivity growth of the past 20 years to sustain growth in GDP per capita.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/images/mckinsey_aging_productivity.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When these productivity challenges are coupled with declining labor force participation rates, the ultimate effect is a deceleration in per capita GDP growth. Future generations could have a lower rate of improvement in living standards than their parents—and in some cases, such as in the Southern Europe cluster, the next generation could be poorer than their parents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;for-younger-workers-capturing-emerging-areas-of-economic-growth-require-new-skills&quot;&gt;For younger workers, capturing emerging areas of economic growth require new skills.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What about the remaining labor force? Here we find significant mismatches between what employees can do and what firms need to be done. In most advanced economies, unemployment rates for the least-skilled are two to four times those of the most highly skilled workers, whether the economy is in recession or recovery. The effects of falling demand for low-skill labor have been especially harsh for younger workers. Today, 75 million young people (aged 15 to 24) who are not in school or college are unemployed, account for 38 percent of the world’s unemployed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For skilled labor, firms are finding a lack of talent—a “STEM shortage.” This is reflected in the time required to fill roles. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.brookings.edu/interactives/still-searching-job-vacancies-and-stem-skills/&quot;&gt;In a Brookings study&lt;/a&gt;, the duration of advertising for a STEM occupation that typically requires a graduate degree is 25 days at the median, 50 days average, and 93 days at the 80th percentile. These search times are much longer than the average for all non-STEM U.S. vacancies, for which the median is just five days, the average is 33, and the 80th percentile is 64. The question of how to tackle these problems—adapting an economy with a large aging population with significant dynamism in the most valued skills—will be a challenge of the next few decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;skills-in-digital-growth-will-require-new-education-models-that-are-promising-but-unproven&quot;&gt;Skills in digital growth will require new education models that are promising, but unproven.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There has been much documentation around occupational skill gaps: for example, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.themanufacturinginstitute.org/Research/Skills-Gap-in-Manufacturing/Skills-Gap-in-Manufacturing.aspx&quot;&gt;in manufacturing&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bls.gov/opub/mlr/2015/article/stem-crisis-or-stem-surplus-yes-and-yes.htm&quot;&gt;in STEM&lt;/a&gt;, and in digital literacy. As a result, many non-traditional workforce development programs have been created in recent years, including online courses (MOOCs) and bootcamp models. Tech training is touted by workforce development policymakers as being at the leading edge of trends such as skills-based hiring, non-traditional learning, and rapid education models. Bootcamps are considered by some to be at the forefront of workforce development more generally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet the field is new, and the lack of comprehensive and concrete data on outcomes and transparency makes much of the tech training hype difficult to verify. Additionally, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jpmorganchase.com/corporate/Corporate-Responsibility/document/JPMC-tech-training-report-web.pdf&quot;&gt;policymakers and employers may be overwhelmed&lt;/a&gt; by the abundance of new training programs. Questions still linger about whether these programs are successfully creating a skilled tech workforce that meets employers’ needs, much less if these programs are fulfilling the promise of economic mobility for participants and creating a workforce that is diverse in gender and race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The rubber hits the road at employment. All this great stuff means nothing if you don’t hire the people at the end.” – Barbara Chang, Code to Work&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a relatively new field, complete data does not exist to evaluate which programs are most effective, making it difficult for employers, participants, and funders to determine their success. The data most programs release do not show whether graduates take jobs in the field, or whether they are still employed several years later. As a result, employers may be missing good job candidates due to limited resources for recruitment and job seekers must rely on anecdotes and unverified statistics to make decisions about whether to participate in a program and which one to choose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-does-it-all-mean&quot;&gt;What does it all mean&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aging populations may be a significant headwind to growth in the subsequent decades. To maintain and exceed current rates of productivity growth, the population will need to more intensively adopt digital skills. Job skills, retraining, and effective certification are particularly important areas of public-private partnerships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additional research, perspective, and detail can be found in the following supporting articles:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bradaallen.github.io/digital-economy-intro/&quot;&gt;Intro: Creating a general framework for current opportunities and challenges.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bradaallen.github.io/digital-economy-part-1/&quot;&gt;Part I: We are in a time of slow productivity and strong incumbents.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bradaallen.github.io/digital-economy-part-3/&quot;&gt;Part III: Technology requires deeper integration into our work lives.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My goal in putting this together was to clarify my own thinking - and to present it in a way that can be challenged and deepened by others. I would be grateful to learn what may resonate (or differ) from your personal perspectives and work.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Demographic and structural barriers to progress exist.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Digital Economy Part I: Slow Productivity &amp;amp; Strong Incumbents</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/digital-economy-part-1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Digital Economy Part I: Slow Productivity &amp; Strong Incumbents" /><published>2017-05-17T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2017-05-17T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/digital-economy-part-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/digital-economy-part-1/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;These articles are part of exploration that started in late 2015 and early 2016. It was a confusing time: autonomous vehicles and Boston Dynamics were frequently in the news and OpenAI was just formed to make sure that the “march towards AGI was safe.” UBI was actively being discussed by Sam Altman and Ray Kurzweil was promoting 10x / exponential thinking. At the same time, economists like Robert Gordon were arguing that we were actually living in a time of low progress.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I tried to develop my own perspective on what was happening, with key conclusions presented &lt;a href=&quot;https://bradaallen.github.io/digital-economy-intro/&quot;&gt;at this link&lt;/a&gt;. Greater detail supporting other conclusions can be found in &lt;a href=&quot;https://bradaallen.github.io/digital-economy-part-2/&quot;&gt;Part II&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://bradaallen.github.io/digital-economy-part-3/&quot;&gt;Part III&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;innovation-is-not-improving-quality-of-life-as-quickly-as-experienced-in-prior-generations&quot;&gt;Innovation is not improving quality of life as quickly as experienced in prior generations.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Digitization has had a profound effect on how we live our lives. It has enabled business model innovations (e.g., e-commerce, SaaS) and redefined how we consume media and interact with one another. At the same time, economists believe we may be living in a time in which the net rate of progress is lower than that of prior generations (see chart below; source McKinsey). What explains this apparent paradox?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/images/mckinsey_productivity.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thesis for this may be that gains in the technology sector have not effectively led to similar innovation in other sectors of the economy. With this, gains in technology alone cannot have a large influence on overall US economic performance: it &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.comptia.org/about-us/newsroom/press-releases/2015/02/10/united-states-tech-industry-employs-6.5-million-in-2014&quot;&gt;only represents ~7% of total GDP&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The performance of US productivity would support this claim. Gains in GDP are divided into two measurements: productivity and labor employment. Productivity, as a rough measure, is the difference between GDP growth and changes in labor employment. For example, in 2014, labor employment grew by 1.7% and GDP grew by 2.4%; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.conference-board.org/retrievefile.cfm?filename=The-Conference-Board-2015-Productivity-Brief.pdf&amp;amp;type=subsite&quot;&gt;“productivity” grew by the difference, 0.7%&lt;/a&gt;. Productivity is considered to be a proxy for innovation, as it should account for excess value that workers create (relative to historical performance). In the United States, over the last 40 years, this measure of productivity has slowed. In fact, &lt;em&gt;the rate of productivity growth from 2011 to 2015 was the slowest since the five-year period ending in 1982.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Economists have been trying to figure out this puzzle for many decades, and it is becoming increasingly important. We know that the &lt;a href=&quot;http://faculty.chicagobooth.edu/chad.syverson/research/productivityslowdown.pdf&quot;&gt;slowdown across countries is not correlated with IT production or use&lt;/a&gt;, suggesting that the problem is not &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.brookings.edu/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/ByrneEtAl_ProductivityMeasurement_ConferenceDraft.pdf&quot;&gt;mismeasurement related to IT goods or services&lt;/a&gt;.  We also know that &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.econ.yale.edu/~nordhaus/homepage/productivityandneweconomy.pdf&quot;&gt;the slowdown has been broad-based across industries&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/2016/04/29/upshot/why-is-productivity-so-weak-three-theories.html&quot;&gt;would be similar if industry weights were held fixed&lt;/a&gt; — it does not reflect a rising share of slow-growth industries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Robert Gordon, an economist, has a theory that, with regard to innovation, the years from 1870-1970 are unparalleled throughout history and advances in ICT in recent decades simply do not compare to the relatively concurrent inventions of electricity, the internal combustion engine, modern sanitation and plumbing, aviation, pharma products, etc. Coupled with this, ICT advances haven’t made the type of broad-based improvements to the economy that these other technologies have—leaving their overall effect on the economy more muted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is this theory a predictor of what will happen in the future? Certainly not. But one can think about the nature of value creation from advances in ICT. By and large, they have focused on automating routine activities. More modern innovations in AI and data science have focused on further, non-routine automation. These technologies key on reducing cost and price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When labor is not able to use the gains from these efficiencies to focus on other, more value-added activities, the role of technology in GDP growth is challenged. As an anecdote, one rationale for the recent merger between Monsanto and Bayer is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wsj.com/articles/behind-the-monsanto-deal-doubts-about-the-gmo-revolution-1473880429&quot;&gt;that farmers’ profit has not improved enough to continue to invest in GMO seeds&lt;/a&gt;. The point is clear: if our economy cannot find the kind of growth that creates a “rising tide for all boats,” we stunt the ability to bring new innovations to market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;current-business-activity-has-a-strong-focus-on-protecting-existing-profit-pools&quot;&gt;Current business activity has a strong focus on protecting existing profit pools.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disruptive technology should lead to a proliferation of new markets and/or significant churn in existing ones. However, this has not been the case: competition in the United States has slowed in recent decades. This has become &lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.duke.edu/collardwexler/files/2015/01/20160414_cea_competition_issue_brief.pdf&quot;&gt;a recent focus of the Council of Economic Advisors&lt;/a&gt;: ROIC is increasing (especially for market leaders), &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.economist.com/blogs/graphicdetail/2016/03/daily-chart-13&quot;&gt;markets are becoming increasingly consolidated&lt;/a&gt;, M&amp;amp;A activity is increasing, and the rate of firm entry (startups) has been decreasing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/images/roic_and_business_turnover.png&quot; /&gt;
	&lt;figcaption&gt;Images from the CEA's competition brief.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To wit: an American firm that was very profitable in 2003 (one with post-tax returns on capital of 15-25%, excluding goodwill) had an 83% chance of still being very profitable in 2013, according to McKinsey. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.economist.com/news/briefing/21695385-profits-are-too-high-america-needs-giant-dose-competition-too-much-good-thing&quot;&gt;In the previous decade the odds were about 50%&lt;/a&gt;. And since 2008, American firms have engaged in one of the largest rounds of mergers in their country’s history, worth $10 trillion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Supporting this, incumbent businesses are using their resources to protect profit—and do so by investing in the continual modernization of their operations. These incremental investments in innovation (e.g., digitization) increase barriers for new entrants as organizations focus on their short-term profit. (Recent papers have noted &lt;a href=&quot;https://faculty.fuqua.duke.edu/~sb135/bio/Science%201%2091%2015.pdf&quot;&gt;a decline in basic and applied research within large corporations&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-does-it-all-mean&quot;&gt;What does it all mean&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to today’s market structures, dynamism and economic shifts will be slow without large shocks to competition. Digital skills will accrue most at incumbent firms, who have the resources to make investments and can create competitive moats. Public institutions should create incentives to spur investment into basic science R&amp;amp;D - we need leadership to focus on long-term sources of growth and diversify areas of productivity within the economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additional research, perspective, and detail can be found in the following supporting articles:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bradaallen.github.io/digital-economy-intro/&quot;&gt;Intro: Creating a general framework for current opportunities and challenges.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bradaallen.github.io/digital-economy-part-2/&quot;&gt;Part II: Aging &amp;amp; unproven learning models are headwinds to growth.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bradaallen.github.io/digital-economy-part-3/&quot;&gt;Part III: Technology requires deeper integration into our work lives.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My goal in putting this together was to clarify my own thinking - and to present it in a way that can be challenged and deepened by others. I would be grateful to learn what may resonate (or differ) from your personal perspectives and work.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">In aggregate, things aren't changing as much as times past.</summary></entry></feed>